Hi, welcome back to our Lam Rim meditations
for our class called "Love in the Time of the Virus".
We've been going through the tenth chapter,
the dedication chapter of Master Shantideva's
Guide to the Bodhisattvas Way of Life.
Today we're in the final week of this course,
and we've reached the final part of that chapter.
It's actually verses 53 to 58.
So, it's the very end of the chapter.
The whole chapter is 58 verses and we're covering the last five verses now, five or six verses.
There are some main ideas here.
We are still doing an act of truth.
So, remember that!
We are thinking about some amazing good karma we've done in the last month or two, in the last few months.
And we are grabbing on to that good seed and then we are kind of using it as a bullet to shoot the virus.
We are doing an act of truth.
We're saying: if it's true that during these difficult times
and especially the early times
when we were all nervous, we were all afraid.
We didn't know what was going to happen.
If it's true that during those difficult times--
in this country we were all out of toilet paper.
I remember Tim gave me some.
I bow to you.
If during those very difficult times you share what you have or you're kind to someone else,
then you have some material, you have a bullet that you can use for your act of truth.
During this meditation, the first part,
we're going to think about some something nice
we did for somebody else during the virus,
during the difficult days, especially.
And then we're going to
take that good karma like Shantideva did--
his good karma was writing the book, by the way,
the first nine chapters,
And then we're going to dedicate it
that something amazing should happen.
And then we'll have a list of amazing things.
Now, the amazing things are centered around this special kind of bodhisattva intention.
And that's called-- it's a strange prayer.
Let's say you're working--
I used to work in a company in New York.
We had a big company about 800 people in the building.
And, let's say I want to do a real bodhisattva thing.
And, by the way, I used to do this kind of thing.
I would go into the bathroom and just sit on top of the toilet and do like a five minute meditation.
So, I would go into the bathroom, close the door, sit on top of the seat, on top of the cover.
Then I would do this five minute meditation.
This is a hard one, it's a strange one and I would think about this company, this busy, busy diamond company.
Hundreds and hundreds of people
in the building right now working hard.
We used to work really hard and of course
there's many problems going on: one lady has got cancer, the other lady had just lost a baby,
This guy is worried about losing his job, this person just had a divorce. All these kind of things in this building.
We all had stress and in this building,
eight hundred people--
everyone's having some kind of thing going on,
some kind of problem going on.
And sitting here in the toilet stall I will suck in like a sponge, I will suck in all of their problems for five minutes, just five minutes.
So, this is like a dharma break you can do.
I like to say that no one ever told me not to go to the toilet even during these intense board meetings with the owners and the investors.
It was okay to stand up and leave if you are going to go to the toilet and no one would stop you.
So, I would use that as an excuse
to do like five minute meditation,
let all the trouble in this building, let all the trouble of 800 people come into my heart, right now.
All coming to me. I will eat all the little and big problems of the people that I work with.
Just do it for five minutes. By the way, don't freak out. It's like a tong len. Of course you should destroy it
with the bright light at the lotus of your heart.
Don't sit there with eight hundred people's problems.
Inside you're going to get sick or something.
Obviously you're supposed to destroy these problems, but you're supposed to be willing to take them,
which is difficult.
Tong len is with one person.
We're talking hundreds of people
or maybe thousands of people.
So, in this last meditation we're going to be doing that kind of act of truth.
If it's true that during the virus I helped someone
then right now may all the problems of all the people in the whole universe, not just the COVID people.
There are billions and billions of planets like this,
all of them, I will take all of their trouble!
Billions and billions of planets worth of beings and not just people, all the animals, birds, insects, bacteria,
I would take all of them.
Probably the COVID is running around wishing he could live also, right?
I would take all--
I'll take the COVID virus' personal problems.
I will take them on myself and happily.
And this is an act of truth.
If it's true that I did something nice during the virus
then, by that power, should I have the power, should I have the strength to take on all the problems of billions of planets worth of people.
If you want an image for it,
we can take it from Seiji's book which is called The Crown of Knives.
In fact, it was an instruction granted to Lord Atisha by his teacher who is Dharma Rakshita.
So, we've been talking about Lord Atisha a lot.
He got a poem from his own teacher just
before he went to this crazy country called Tibet
to take care of the people there.
The teacher said you're going to need this poem.
Here's a poem to make you feel better when you go to all this wild Tibetans.
In that text they referred to a thing called
The Crown of Knives.
Sometimes they call Wheel of Sharp Weapons.
I like Crown of Knives better
because of an ancient story which we translated.
And by the way, that book is coming out soon.
I think the translation was finished yesterday.
The final editing has to be done.
But there's a story in an ancient sutra called
All the Kinds of karma. Karma Vibanga,
which talks about all the correlations there are.
There's a story in there of a young man who decided to take on the pain of the world.
He was about to be murdered
by a special ninja star wheel.
A big one, that was about to chop into his head like a crown of knives. And just before that crown of knives came to his head, he made a prayer:
May I take all the pain of all the people.
Especially my mother and my father.
Here you see the wheel.
We're using this wheel picture here.
So, let's go! Let's start!
Just remember the general strategy.
We're going to think
of a good thing we did during the virus.
Then we're going to do an act of truth.
If it's true that I helped people during the virus,
that I was unselfish during the virus
then may my dreams come true.
What are your dreams?
My dream is that I can take all the pain of the whole Universe on me.
That's kind of a strange dream but I hope it works.
So, here we go!
Get ready for meditation, sit up straight.
I like a small smile on my face.
And the forehead is relaxed.
Just be here.
Don't think about all the stuff you have to do.
We all have stuff to do and we all die in the middle of it. So, don't get too attached to it.
Pull in your tummy.
Shoulders back. Hands back on the thighs.
And we'll do ten long exhales to get into the meditation.
So, please remember some kindness you did for somebody else during the time of the virus.
Now we're going to do an act of truth.
If it's true that I paid this kindness
to people during the virus.
Then, first of all, may I meet Manjushri,
may I meet that exquisite angel.
Beautiful, beautiful angel who is made of all the wisdom of the Buddhas, all the wisdom of all the Buddhas
May I meet Manjushri.
If it's true that I was kind during the virus, then may I personally meet Manjushri face to face.
And may I be like him,
may I have this bodhisattva intention.
May I have this experience of meeting all beings
and assuring them that I will take care of them.
Here comes the big part of this meditation.
If it's true I did do some small kindness during the virus,
then may all the problems of all beings ripen on me.
May I take all their bad seeds into me.
And it feels very good.
It sounds frightening, it sounds like it would be a lot of trouble and normally we are trying to escape trouble.
But there's a certain beauty, extreme beauty
to purposely and anonymously
taking other people's problems away from them
and taking them on ourselves.
It's a little difficult to start.
But once you do it, it feels so right.
Then it becomes easy
and it becomes extremely satisfying.
If it's true I did a little thing
during the virus times for somebody else,
then may I have the blessing of the ability to take on other people's troubles
This is a big universe, this planet is not the only place there is.
There are countless other bodhisattvas in the universe.
There are many, many, countless, cannot count them.
Amazing wonderful people
on many, many different planets.
So, let's do an act of truth for them
which is what master Shantideva does here.
If it's true that I did a small good thing
during the days of the virus,
if I had love during the time of the virus,
then may all the dreams and all the plans
of all those bodhisattvas to help the people
on their own planet come true.
May their dreams, may there plans come true.
By the power of my good deed.
These ideas are extremely unusual for someone.
For all of us to sit here and pray
that people's troubles should come to us,
it's a very, very unusual philosophy,
unusual way of life.
But if it became more widespread in this world
then the whole world would be much happier.
It's much more--
it makes you much happier to serve other people
than to take things from other people.
It makes your whole life sweet and fulfilled.
If only this kind of thinking,
strange, beautiful thinking, could spread in this world.
I will do an act of truth.
If I was nice to someone during the days of the virus,
then this strange beautiful idea,
that I should take the troubles of other people, should spread in this world and make this world a happy world.
In the final verse of the
Guide to the Bodhisattva's Way of Life
Master Shantideva bows down
to his own teacher, who is Manjushri, really.
So, we can do that together.
Let's bow down to this divine being who is made of love,
bodhichitta
and an understanding of seeds and emptiness.
Okay, then slowly open your eyes.
Take a good stretch.
We'll do this meditation for the whole last week.
Try to do it twice a day.
You'll be very happy.
And try to read that chapter or if you want to
you can listen to the recording.
And try to listen to that once or twice a day.
See you then!